Hi, and welcome to this short video
where we will look at how you can find
and fix bugs within your software.
So there are many, many numbers of
different techniques and ways to identify
and fix bugs, but there are some of more
common ones that are used by developers
and testers within software development.
And, but one of the first things that
you need to consider is so, How do
you know if a bug is valid or not?
So, it may be a case that, you know, you've
got a tester and you'll identify a bug that is
not really a bug, and the bug's marked invalid.
But how does he know it's not really a bug?
This tends to happen when the functionality
that is being tested works okay.
But the tester isn't actually sure.
He still thinks there's
something not right with it.
And so then to check if that bug
is valid, they'll make sure that it
wasn't caused by the code itself.
So, sorry, that it was caused by the code
itself rather than an external factor or
utilising the code in a way that wasn't.
intended.
So another way of thinking about this as
well is that sometimes a tester will identify
a bug and it's actually not in scope.
So when we're talking about in scope
and out of scope, is it something
that you've been asked to test?
Is there a test plan and is that?
Element of the code involved or part of that
test plan And if it's not it may be that it that
they're already aware of it And it is an out of
it's out of scope And it may still be worthwhile
reporting that but then obviously the developer
when they look at it again say yes We can just
ignore that because it we expected that to happen.
It wasn't in the scope of that
test So that is an invalid bug.
So what are the common sources of bugs?
So there are Half a dozen of the most
common sources of bugs and functional
errors are one of the most common.
So what is a functional error?
So, this is where the software
does not behave as expected.
So, an example of this would be if you
press the Save button, but the data
that had been entered isn't saved.
Similarly, you could have a Save As button.
It's basically anything that, sort of, when
you're expecting the software to do something,
and it's carrying out a function, if it doesn't
do what is expected, that is a functional error.
And it is one of the most common errors out there.
You then have syntax or type errors and typos
are a very common one where you fail to add a
simple character or a letter and that is then
picked up as a type or the syntax error that as
you can see there's a an example there and it it
mentions that this is caught by the most commonly
caught by compilers which will if you put your
write your code run it through the compiler.
The compiler can't understand it.
It will give you an error message, which
is a really good function of the compiler.
So as you can see here, the quotation marks
there on Python are missing on the end of Python.
So it's telling you that there is a syntax error.
while scanning the string literal.
So it's telling you exactly where it
is, that little indication mark there.
And again, these are quite common errors.
A lot of the type errors are just
quite simply a case of proofreading the
work, and syntax errors, very similar.
You're using the wrong syntax,
or the syntax is incomplete.
Logic or calculation errors.
Again, these are quite common and it basically
represents a mistake in the software flow
which causes it to behave incorrectly.
So, it could even crash the software.
So, not like syntax errors, these will
not prevent a program from compiling.
So, as you saw in the previous example.
The compiler gave you a warning on a logic
or a calculation error, it will still run
through and it could actually end up getting
caught in what's called an infill loop.
And these tend to occur when you've assigned
a value to the wrong variable of another
example, dividing two numbers instead of
multiplying resulting in an incorrect output.
So again, it tends to be
due to poorly written code.
And the software will behave erratically or you'll
constantly get the wrong outputs due to the fact
that the calculations and the logic is wrong.
It tends not to actually, um, be, they can
be quite difficult to find because as I
mentioned, the compiler doesn't pick these up.
So what are the common sources of bugs?
You've also got...
Unit level bugs and these are bugs
that occur in a small section of code.
So you've learned about unit testing previously
again because these are small elements of code
These can be quite easy to identify because if
you're testing the actual unit level of code It
does make it easy to find you're not having to
go through pages and pages of the actual code.
It's just there you're testing that unit,
which obviously the benefits of that are
that you are only working with 5, 6, 7,
lines of code maximum for a unit level.
System level integration bugs.
And again, this tends to happen when you've got
More than one coder or people in different people
in the development team writing different pieces
of code And they fail to interact with each other.
So they can be hard to fix Because you tend
to find that um, if this is the case of that
You've got code that was written by different
developers or even different pieces of software
Then it isn't easy to sort of find out exactly
what the problem is can be quite Difficult,
um, you know, examples of the type of bug that
this can cause a byte swap, non message parsing
or even memory overflow issues can be caused
with these system level integration bugs.
Out of bounds bugs.
So, again, this is a.
An example of this is when the sort of the end
user, the person using the product, interacts with
the software in, in ways that weren't expected.
So it's actually like sort of, um, entering
parameters that were outside of the, the
remit of what the software wants to do.
So, um, say you expect to.
Input of five or six numbers and somebody keeps
putting in 25 numbers and it would, you know, or
inputting incorrect data types into the fields.
So inputting numbers when, uh, there
should have been text, but that hasn't been
considered when the code was being written.
And obviously that can cause quite a few.
Errors and issues, but again, you will find
that most of these are considered when you're
writing the software So there should be, um,
far less of these than the other common types
of bugs So we've looked at different types
of bugs and how they occur, but one of the
things there is so how do you fix the problems?
how do you fix these when you find the bugs and
One of the ways that could this be done is the
incremental and bottom up programming development.
So again, this is talking about you
develop the code incrementally and carry
out tests after adding each piece of code.
So this is obviously quite straightforward,
but it's, and it keeps things
simple, but it can be very effective.
So you create a unit of code
or a small element of code.
It's tested.
Does it work?
Yes.
Okay.
Then go, go on and create the next piece of code.
Does that work?
Yes, it works.
Does it work with the previous piece of code?
So they're working together and again, it will
eliminate the potential issues that you may find.
Error detection tools.
So one of the things that there's an awful
lot of error detection tools out there.
Um, They're basically designed to find either
errors at the run time or at compile time.
So you've got your compilation where it
picks up errors while it's compiling or you
get the detection tools which will pick up
errors when the program is actually being run.
And certain examples of that, you've got Purify,
which is a, it's identifying memory errors,
um, such as invalid access or memory leaks.
You've got Escape Java and Spec Hash,
which are tools that, uh, you can use.
To, you know, give the general, it checks
the general user specifications, and then
you've also got to consider data flow
analysis, which detects violations of
safety properties within the software.
So there's quite a lot of, um, ways
of error detection tools out there.
Some are purely designed for different
types of programming languages.
Some are a bit of a catch all.
Bug clustering.
Bug clustering is quite straightforward.
It is what it says.
You, you, you group the, the bugs,
uh, the classes of related bugs.
So if you're getting large numbers of
errors, if you class them into, um, put
them all into one classification, so if
they're all very similar errors, and then
you can just examine one of the bugs.
So it may be a case that
you're getting 50 or 60 errors.
But if they're all the same type of errors, you
just need to look at one and that would probably
give you a good idea of how that can be resolved.
Scientific method.
This is quite a complex one where you have to
form a hypothesis for the cause of the bug that
is consistent with the observed data, then design
and run a simple test to check the hypothesis.
So quite a complex one that it may want to carry
out some further research on that one because
it is quite a difficult one to explain, but.
It's basically that you will
then, um, create the hypothesis.
If it's incorrect, you will then come up
with another hypothesis and then continue
the process until you come to a solution.
If you've got to think about, this is
like the simplification of a process or
a, that'll allow you to break it down.
And so if it's, if you create a hypothesis
and it's incorrect, okay, let's look at the
next one and then the next one and the next
one until you find the one that will work.
Which brings us on to problem simplification.
So, in this one here, again, similar to
using the scientific method, what you'll
do is you'll eliminate portions of the
code that aren't relevant to the bug.
So, I'll put an example on here
where if a function, which is fun,
so you've got that function there.
If it's given you an error, try eliminating
the calls to G, H, and K one at a time to
determine which one is causing the problem.
So it's very similar to If you find that, um, a
good analogy would be a Christmas tree lights.
If the Christmas tree lights aren't
working, you go around and you
test the connection for each one.
Screw them out, screw them
in, make sure they're in.
And ultimately you will find the error.
And backtracking, again, it's
a quite a straightforward one.
Start from the point where the problem
occurred and go back through the code
to see how it might have happened.
So this is basically you're just looking at
that code again and working your way backwards
to see whereabouts in the code that this
Error is, is occurring, but again, this can
be very, very time consuming if you've got a
large portion of code or if you've got quite
a significant amount of code, backtracking can
be a very, very time, um, intense activity.
Error logs, and you may have heard of error logs,
so error logs tend to point to the part of the
code that's causing the issue, so it's a very
precise way of finding errors within code, and
it allows you to check logs from previous, um,
running of the software to see if other similar
issues have come up, so this is something where
you would find if you are doing maintenance on a
piece of software, error logs will be something
that you would look at and see, right, how many
times has this occurred in the previous 30 days?
So, you know, error logs are very useful.
Again, we've got the backtracking, which
is asking you to start from the point
where the problem occurred and go back
through the code and binary search.
So, Binary search is asking you to explore the
code using a divide and conquer approach, so
If you've got a large piece of code, you may
place a checkpoint halfway through the code So
if the error doesn't show up at that point So
if nothing's happened as you run the code up to
that point it means that the bugs gonna occur in
the the second half and This can, or you could
break it down into, break the code down into
five chunks or six chunks and then run it and
it allows you to, when you repeat the process,
it can quickly get you to the actual problem.
So we've looked at the different types of bugs and
the common ways that bugs have happened and how
you can resolve them, but how do you ensure that
the similar problems won't occur in the future?
So one of the things there is that if you're
getting, um, a bug occurring in a piece of code.
Check all those areas of code that relate to that.
So, again, it depends if you're looking at inputs.
If you're getting errors on input areas of
code, check all of the input areas of code.
And then you've got Error logs, you can add them
if they don't exist, because if you have error
logs, that means that you can then identify
it and you can go back and see that if it's
happened previously, and then you could also
look at using, um, the tracing system for bugs.
Now, the tracing system is really
useful because it allows you to track
if bugs happen elsewhere in the code.
So again, this is relevant if you're
part of a large team, you may be
aware of a bug and you fix it.
And other people wouldn't be aware of that.
So using a tracking system helps other team
members to quickly fix any problems because
they can look and say, yes, you've had that
problem before and look for it and then
be able to identify it and rectify that.
So let's look at the benefits
of variable watching.
So what is variable watching?
So basically, a watch variable, it's any
item of data in a program that a program
wants to observe while you're debugging.
So what you would do is, so, when you think
about that you're running a program, Even when
you're using a debugger, you start the program,
and it starts at the beginning, and it continues
until completion, or until an error occurs.
So, the debugger may tell you there's
an error, but not where the error is.
So, what you can do to track down
the exact location, you can use
what's called variable watching.
And you insert sort of a watchpoint or a
breakpoint to stop the program execution whenever
the value of a particular expression, which is
the watchpoint or breakpoint expression, changes.
So, these sort of, these tell the debugger
where to halt the execution of your
program so you can see what's going on.
So it may be that...
You want to halt the code whenever there's
an input, um, from one of the users.
So whenever there's a variable being
inputted, you may want to test up
to that point or test that point.
So you would then set a variable
watch on a specific line.
Where that variable is being input and it allows
you to um give lines of code You can have multiple
breakpoints within the code and it allows you
to inspect carry out those inspections You know,
there's quite a few benefits of variable watching
So it reduces the time to debug the code because
you're yeah, you're looking for specific things
It gives you a better understanding of the code
which enables you to consider how the code can
be tamed more easily so When we're talking about
there is that you could then, um, look at the
code and think, right, if I had it done this a
different way, I could have made it much simpler,
or I could write the piece of code in a different
way, which would then allow you to have a more
streamlined, and, and the code would work better
and would be easier to maintain in the future.
And you can learn how to build smarter tests
so that you can identify bugs more easily.
So it, it's a learning curve.
So when you're using.
Variable Watching.
As with most of the, um, the ways that
you, you know, carry out your testing.
You, it's a learning process all the time,
and you'll learn how to build smarter tests.
So then we'll look at the
benefits of compiler warnings.
So, compiler warnings, one of the beauties
is that it it, it allows you to fix
books before the software's released.
Um, you know, the compiler will give you warnings.
So if you can utilize the compiler and take
note of those warnings, it will ensure that
you can get those bugs fixed before it goes
out to the, the customer or the client.
And which then obviously you get a happy
customer, a happy client and less complaints.
And again, it gives you the opportunity
to give you to create simpler and
easier, I mean, to maintain code.
So as you're, as you're learning all the
time, you know, the complexity of the
code, it may be relevant that it has to be
that complex, but does it, it gives you an
opportunity to look at it and see if I did
this in a different way because of the way
the warnings are indicating what the error is.
You gain a greater understanding of the code.
So the more you test something, the more and
the more errors you see of the way the code
works, it gives you a better understanding of
that code, which then obviously can lead to, um,
creating simpler and easier to maintain code and.
It gives you a faster build time and increases
productivity, which is very important in
today's world of coding and development,
because there are normally quite tight
deadlines and timescales to work towards.
And the benefits of unit tests.
So we've obviously looked at units and
unit testing, um, quite a bit as we've
looked at things because they are a very,
very small component to test and unit
tests do make the process much more agile.
One of the beauties of unit testing there is that
you tend to find that in software development,
people are working in an Agile environment.
So when you're working in Agile, it'll,
you tend to, you build tests that allow
you to make changes much more easily.
You tend to find that also the quality
of the code tends to improve because
you're obviously testing out small units.
And it allows you to look at that
code and say, can it be done better?
Because you're only testing small
elements, the benefits are there's
that you can find the software bugs
early, and it provides documentation.
So, one of the things there is when you're looking
to learn what functionality is provided by a
unit, and how to use it, you can look at the
test again, and the basic understanding of the
unit's interface, which allows you to, you get
that documentation relating to what the software
is doing or what that piece of code is doing.
Design, it allows you to, you know, when you
focus on design, it tends to allow you to
design code in a way that is much better.
It works better and it reduces costs
because one of the things there is, which
is, you know, can be quite critical.
It is important that.
If you can find bugs early and you can
make the process more agile, you will take
less time to produce the code, test the
code, refactor the code if necessary, which
obviously leads to a reduction in the cost.